Souvik Das

🛮 (+1) 902-817-5690 | 🗷 souvikdas0718@gmail.com | 🄏 souvikdas0718.github.io | 🖸 souvikdas0718 | 🛅 souvik-das-04996ba6

Summary

Software professional with four years of industrial experience in Software Development and DevOps Engineering. I have a thorough understanding and experience working on:

Big Data Technologies Cloud Technologies Data Structures CI/CD Pipelines Data Analysis
Data Warehousing Data Modelling Serverless Computing Code reviewing and debugging System Design

Technical Skills

Languages: Java, Python, Node.js, JavaScript, Perl, Unix Shell Scripting

Hadoop Ecosystem and Frameworks: Hadoop, YARN, MapReduce, Apache Pig, Hive, Sqoop, Zookeeper, Oozie **Cloud Frameworks & APIs:** Sails.js, REST API, AWS Services, Microsoft Azure Services, OpenStack, Heroku

Web technologies: HTML, CSS, React, Express, Bootstrap

Cloud technologies: AWS Elastic Beanstalk, EC2, AWS Lambda, Cognito, RDS, AWS S3, API Gateway, Cognito, Azure, Docker

BI & Visualization Tools: Tableau and IBM Cognos, Grafana, QlikView. **Databases:** RDBMS, MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Neo4j, FireBase

Work Experience [3 Years 11 months]

BlackBerry, Big Data Developer Student, Waterloo, Canada

May. 2021 - Present

- Transitioned existing Hive Server 1 script to Hive Server 2 for CDP7 upgrade.
- Wrote Hive queries to transform data for further downstream processing.
- Worked with Sqoop to ingest retrieve data from various RDBMS like Oracle DB MySQL.
- Designed, created, tested, and maintained the complete data management processing systems.
- Defined DDL statement and stored procedures for storing Data to Oracle DB.
- Defined bash scripts for batch processing of hive warehouse data and enabled fail-over system notification to groups.
- Collaborating with the team for future Big Data cluster migration to AWS cloud using EMR.

Infosys, Senior Systems Engineer, Bangalore, India

Aug. 2016 - Dec. 2019

- Designed and deployed automated Python scripts for data dump collection using cronjobs as part of a migration project reducing human efforts by eight hours required for each migration.
- Specialized in following 100% coverage of projects adhering to Software Development Life Cycle model using Perl, Python, and database in various areas like requirements gathering, analysis, design, development, implementation, and maintenance.
- Developed an automated Client Access Governance System using Perl that lowered manual work by over 90%
- Built a Python automation tool to perform the internal DNS operations that increased efficiency by 50%.
- Performed test automation using Hewlett Packard (QC and ALM) for requirements and bug tracking, including a 100% coverage of Unit and Integration testing.
- Collaborated with a five-member team to develop a Web application for tracking Telstra Broadband customer's data usage.

Education

Master of Applied Computer Science, DALHOUSIE UNIVERSITY, CANADA

Jan. 2020 - Dec. 2021

- · Participated in Aviation Technology Hackathon conducted by Shift Key labs and Halifax Stanfield Airport.
- Supervised and conducted labs as a Teaching Assistant and Marker for CSCI 5410 Serverless Computing course to 100 students.

B.E Computer Science Engineering, SATHYABAMA UNIVERSITY, INDIA

Aug. 2012 - May. 2016

• Organized technical events, workshops as a member of the Computer Science club.

Projects

MapReduceAndTwitterAnalysis TECH STACK: HADOOP MAPREDUCE, AWS, PYTHON, IBM COGNOS

- Analyzed the raw data fetched from MongoDB clusters to perform semantic and sentiment analysis.
- · Using Apache Spark and Hadoop MapReduce framework, determined the frequency of keywords in the data.

DalhousieHockeyLeague TECH STACK: JAVA, SQL, GRADLE, GITLAB

- Built a java console-based hockey simulation game by maintaining GitFlow, version control system, and perform build, test, CI/CD continuous
 integration, and deployments on two Timberlea servers using GIT.
- Followed best practices, coding standards, 100 percent Test-Driven Development coverage, S.O.L.I.D principles, design patterns, code reviews, code refactoring techniques to write maintainable code.

Learning Management System TECH STACK: REACT.JS, FLASK, AWS (LEX, SNS, SQS, LAMBDA) | GCP PUB/SUB

- Developed an Online Learning Management System, where online users can form chat groups and interactive UI to publish and subscribe messages, interactive FAQ chatbot, obtain a sentimental analysis of the chat messages and generate a word cloud.
- · Coupled multi-cloud platforms, Google and Amazon, using AWS Lambda, AWS API Gateway, and GCP Cloud Functions.

Find Adobe tech stack: React, Node. Js, Mongodb, Heroku, Gitlab

- A website that helps users to find rented accommodation in a city based on their requirements.
- Designed the home page and the functionalities of hiring and reviewing the accommodations of the application.

Certifications

THE ULTIMATE HANDS-ON HADOOP-TAME YOUR BIG DATA BY FRANK KANE

Sep. 22, 2021

Udemy- UC-dec6de22-b5e2-4183-b2eb-763e501cdd4c